Guide to the Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority metrorail specifications records, 1962-1980 MS2021
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority metrorail specifications
1962-1980
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MS2021
18 Linear Feet
The WMATA Metrorail Specifications collection is comprised primarly of technical specifications and contracts related to the construction of Metrorail. The collection consists of unbound letter-size documents, bound letter-size reports and specifications, oversize reports and specifications, and blueprints.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
The Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority Metrorail Specifications Collection was donated by the Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority to the Gelman Library in January 1985
Historical or Biographical Note
The Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority, WMATA, with central offices in Washington, DC, is the private agency charged with the coordination and operation of mass transit in the National Capital Region. This area includes Montgomery and Prince George's Counties in Maryland, Arlington, the District of Columbia, and Fairfax County in Virginia.
The Interim Board of Directors of WMATA first met in mid-October, 1966, chaired by Brig. Gen. Jackson Graham, formerly Engineering Commissioner for the District. WMATA was formally established on February 20, 1967. WMATA formally received its charter in September 1967.
WMATA superseded the National Capital Transportation Agency (NCTA); a federal agency established by President Eisenhower in 1960 and inherited the bus and rail plans of the NCTA. For bus operations, WMATA bought out the routes from the private bus companies operating within its purview (with the exception of Montgomery County's "Ride-On" system) and established a single operation, Metrobus, to serve in their place.
For the creation of Metrorail, popularly known as "the Metro," routes, designs, and plans were finalized by the late 1960s. Work on the subway component began immediately upon the creation of WMATA. DeLeuw, Cather were retained as chief engineering consultants. The firm of Harry Weese and Associates were named chief architectural consultants. Weese was sent on a worldwide tour of subway systems, in order to draw inspiration and ideas for possible station architecture. The final design, agreed upon by a special committee that included the District of Columbia Board of Fine Arts and several artists and architects, was proposed in 1968.
First ground was broken for the subway above the future Judiciary Square station on December 9, 1969. The Metro ran its first day of revenue service, on the abbreviated Red Line beginning at Dupont Circle, in June 1976. Public response was enthusiastic. The system was a highlight of the Bicentennial celebrations one month later, during which it transported thousands of visitors.
Collection Scope and Content
The WMATA Metrorail Specifications collection is so named because the bulk of the collection is technical specifications and contracts related to the construction of Metrorail. The collection consists of unbound letter-size documents, bound letter-size reports and specifications, oversize reports and specifications, and blueprints.
The collection is an artificial one, consisting of several distinct and unrelated types of documents. The earliest documents date from 1962, and were generated by the WMATA's predecessor agency, the NCTA. Most of these deal with highway development. The bulk of the material dates from 1972-78 and contains of a distinct series of oversize and letter-size bound volumes. These volumes are contract specifications for different sections of Metrorail tunnels, and each bears the name of the contractor that won the bid, as well as the contract number. The collection's third district group of documents consists of minutes of meetings, and related documents, generated by meetings of the Board of Directors and with individual contractors.
The collection's Reports and, especially, Specifications series are highly technical engineering documents. They are valuable for their comprehensive engineering detail and descriptions, through which the evolution, design and construction of the Metro system can be studied in detail. Not all routes, nor all sections along one route, are covered in the available contract specifications. The meeting minutes are valuable for their insight into administrative planning. However, the Board of Directors minutes are present (and presumed complete) only for 1971 and 1974, and the contractor meeting minutes are incomplete for the years covered, namely 1972 through 1978, with several months missing altogether.
Researchers are also advised that six titles, removed from the Metrorail Specifications Collection, have been processed elsewhere as shelved items. Consult library indexes for these titles. The are: "New York City Transit Authority Invitation to Contractors" for Contracts C-213-1 through C-213-3; Contract R-30-A; Contract R-33; and Contract R-40; "District of Columbia Department of Highways and Traffic, Standard Specifications for Highways and Structures", 1974; and "State of Maryland, State Roads Commission, Specifications for Materials, Highways, Bridges, and Incidental Structures", March 1968.
Collection Organization
Organized into four series: Meeting minutes, Reports, Specifications, and Oversize documents.
Roads; Express highways; Bridges; Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority; Local transit; Transportation; Subways; Washington (D.C.); National Capital Transportation Agency (U.S.); Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority
- Meeting minutes, 1971-1978; MS2021 Series 1; 1 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains meeting minutes for the Board of Directors and meeting minutes for the contractors. The materials cover the dates 1971-78. In addition to the minutes the Board of Directors section has additional documents used by the WMATA Board at meetings. The contractors minutes are for meetings with various contractors working for WMATA. All these minutes provide a valuable reference for senior Authority decision making.
  - Board of Directors: Meeting Minutes, Board of Directors, 1971 January (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
  - Board of Directors: Meeting Minutes, Board of Directors, 1971 March (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Board of Directors: Meeting Minutes, Board of Directors, 1971 April (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Board of Directors: Meeting Minutes, Board of Directors, 1971 May (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Board of Directors: Meeting Minutes, Board of Directors, 1971 June (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Board of Directors: Meeting Minutes, Board of Directors, 1971 July (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Board of Directors: Meeting Minutes, Board of Directors, 1971 August (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Board of Directors: Meeting Minutes, Board of Directors, 1971 September (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Board of Directors: Meeting Minutes, Board of Directors, 1971 October (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Board of Directors: Meeting Minutes, Board of Directors, 1971 November (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Board of Directors: Meeting Minutes, Board of Directors, 1971 December (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Board of Directors: Meeting Minutes, Board of Directors, 1974 January (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Board of Directors: Meeting Minutes, Board of Directors, 1974 February (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Board of Directors: Meeting Minutes, Board of Directors, 1974 February (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Board of Directors: Meeting Minutes, Board of Directors, 1974 March (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Board of Directors: Meeting Minutes, Board of Directors, 1974 April (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Board of Directors: Meeting Minutes, Board of Directors, 1974 May (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Board of Directors: Meeting Minutes, Board of Directors, 1974 June (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Board of Directors: Meeting Minutes, Board of Directors, 1974 July (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Board of Directors: Meeting Minutes, Board of Directors, 1974 August (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Board of Directors: Meeting Minutes, Board of Directors, 1974 September (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Board of Directors: Meeting Minutes, Board of Directors, 1974 October (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Board of Directors: Meeting Minutes, Board of Directors, 1974 November (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Contractors: Meeting Minutes, Board of Directors, 1974 December (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Contractors: Meeting Minutes, Contractors, 1972 January-1972 March (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Contractors: Meeting Minutes, Contractors, 1973 April-1973 May (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Contractors: Meeting Minutes, Contractors, 1972 January-1972 August (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Contractors: Meeting Minutes, Contractors, 1973 September-1973 December (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Contractors: Meeting Minutes, Contractors, 1973 January-1973 November (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Contractors: Meeting Minutes, Contractors, 1974 January (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Contractors: Meeting Minutes, Contractors, 1974 May-1974 August (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Contractors: Meeting Minutes, Contractors, 1975 July-1975 December (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Contractors: Meeting Minutes, Contractors, 1976 January (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Contractors: Meeting Minutes, Contractors, 1976 February-1976 March (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Contractors: Meeting Minutes, Contractors, 1976 April-1976 July (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Contractors: Meeting Minutes, Contractors, 1976 July-1977 September (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Contractors: Meeting Minutes, Contractors, 1977 October-1978 March (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Reports, 1962-1981; MS2021 Series 2; 3 Linear feet
  This series contains bound volumes that fall within four main sections including budget and finances, handbooks and manuals, miscellaneous, and transit system development. These volumes are less technical than the specifications series. The documents are primarily text with supporting illustrations. The material covers the dates 1962-81.
  The budget and finances section contains reports from various WMATA sources that detail projected or actual departmental or overall expenses. Handbooks and manuals consists of a construction safety manual. The miscellaneous section includes environmental impact studies and proposed routes. The transit system development section consists of reports detailing development of the Metro system.
  - Budget and Finances: Budget and Finances: Budget Estimates, Fiscal Year 1967, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Budget and Finances: Budget Estimates, Fiscal Year 1968, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Budget and Finances: Gross Estimate, Virginia Proposed Rapid Rail System, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Budget and Finances: Gross Estimate, Washington, DC Proposed Rapid Rail System, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Budget and Finances: Metro Capital Costs, February, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Budget and Finances: Metro Traffic Revenue and Operating Costs, 1971 February (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Budget and Finances: Salaries and Expenses, Fiscal Year 1968, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Budget and Finances: Supplemental Estimates, Fiscal Year 1966, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Budget and Finances: Supplemental Report, Lines 2b, 3b, and 7c, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Budget and Finances: Supplemental Report, Lines 11A-7b, 11A-8b, and 11A-8c, 1967 September (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Reports, Handbooks and Manuals: Construction Safety Manual, Metro System, Part I, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Reports, Handbooks and Manuals: Construction Safety Manual, Metro System, Parts II and III, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Reports, Handbooks and Manuals: Safety Manual, Part I, 1971 April (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Reports, Handbooks and Manuals: Safety Manual, Parts II and III, 1971 April (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Reports, Handbooks and Manuals: Technical Manual, Installation Planning Emergency Construction, 1971 March (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Airlie IIA System, Part 1: Action Program, Phase III Original System Study, October, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Airport Master Plans, Department of Transportation, 1971 February (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Annual Report, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Case Study, Use of Excess Land and Air Rights, 1962 November (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Environmental Impact Study, Metro J and H Route to Springfield and Franconia, 1975 February (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Extracts from a Report to the NCTA Office of Engineering, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Extracts from a Report to the NCTA Office of Engineering, Silver Spring-Rockville Route and Alexandria-Springfield Route, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Filing System Manual, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Final Negative Declaration of the Department of Transportation, 1976 April (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Impact: Metrospace 3 Symposium, Summary and Proceedings, 1971 June (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Impact: A Working Document for Metrospace 3 Symposium, 1971 June (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Metro Property Utilization, Volume 1, 1968 July (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Metropolitan Washington Airports Policy, Supplement to Draft Environmental Impact Statement, United States Department of Transportation and the FAA, 1980 January (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Organizational Charts, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Preliminary Draft Report on Operating Concepts, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Procurement Memorandum Number 1, NCTA-PM-1, 1965 October (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Public Hearing Transcript of Proceedings, 3rd Street SW to Anacostia River, 1972 November (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Report from the Department of the Army, Technical Manual: Installations, Master Planning Principles, and Procedures, 1970 November (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Research Information, Social and Environmental Implications of Transit Centers, NYCTA, 1981 February (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Resolution of the Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority, 1967 August (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - "The Role of the Engineering Community in the Public Decision-Making Process," Engineer's Joint Council, 1967 October (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Sections E003-E005, Environmental Impact Study, Greenbelt E Route, 1974 December (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Technical Note 64-19, Discussion of Transit Car Features, 1964 June (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Technical Note 64-20, Evaluation of Transit Car Proposals, 1964 June (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Technical Note 64-23, On-Board Energy Storage in Rapid Rail Transit, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Technical Report, Prospective Growth of the Washington Metropolitan Area and its Central Core, Volume 1, 1963 August (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Technical Report, Prospective Growth of the Washington Metropolitan Area and its Central Core, Volume 2, Methodological Index, 1963 August (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Technical Report, Study of Traffic Control Systems, Reports 211, 212, and 214, 1964 April (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Urban Renewal Plan for the Southwest Urban Renewal Area, Project C, Sptil 1968, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - WMATA Compact, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Transit System Development: Construction, Rail Rapid Transit System, Fiscal Year 1968, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Transit System Development: "Feasibility of Alignment for the Potomac River Crossing", 1966 August (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Transit System Development: Final Report on Rail Rapid Transit on the Alexandria-Springfield Route, 1963 March (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Transit System Development: Lea Transit Compendium, Heavy Tail Transit, Volume II Number 6, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Transit System Development: NCTA Technical Report, Study of Bus Rapid Transit Operations for the National Capital Region, 1963 July (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Transit System Development: Proposal for State Highways, Department of Transportation and the Commonwealth of Virginia, 1972 March (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Transit System Development: Report to the President, Volume I, Engineering, 1962 November (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Transit System Development: Report to the President, Volume II, Use of Railroad Facilities, 1962 November (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Transit System Development: Report to the President, Volume III, Traffic Forecasting, 1962 November (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Transit System Development: Report to the President, Volume IV, Model for Estimating Travel Mode Usage, 1962 November (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Transit System Development: Report to the President, Volume V, System Planning, 1962 November (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Transit System Development: Report to the President, Volume VI, Organization and Finance, 1962 November (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Transit System Development: Safety Study of Metro/Chessie Operations in a Common Corridor, Volume 1, Report, 1975 August (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Transit System Development: Safety Study of Metro/Chessie Operations in a Common Corridor, Volume 2, Appendices, 1975 August (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Transit System Development: Special Conditions, Section 2, Construction Contracts, 1971 March (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Transit System Development: Special Conditions, Section 3, Technical Provisions, 1971 March (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Transit System Development: Special Conditions, Section 3, Technical Provisions, 1971 March (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Transit System Development: Summary Report on the Transit Development Program, 1963 May (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Transit System Development: "Survey of Commuter Attitudes Toward Transit Systems," Volume 1, 1963 March (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Transit System Development: "Survey of Commuter Attitudes Toward Transit Systems," Volume 2, 1963 July (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Transit System Development: "Survey of Commuter Attitudes Toward Transit Systems," Volume 3 B, Technology and Urban Transportation", 1962 June (Box 9, Folder 8)
- Specifications, 1956-1974; MS2021 Series 3; 4.5 Linear feet
  This series is comprised of documents that contain diagrammatic explanations of Metrorail route contracts and other technical matters. The dates covered are 1956-71.
  The section for bridges, highways, and roads contains volumes that detail the construction and layout of non-rail routes. The miscellaneous section includes a route feasibility study and construction designs. Rail rapid transit specifications are those that deal exclusively with Metrorail routes and contracts. The route designs cover the routes themselves. The support equipment documents contain contracts issued for equipment such as fire extinguishers and kiosks.
  These reports and specifications provide a useful technical adjunct to the more administrative documents found in other Metro-related collections. They pinpoint projected starting and completion dates, names of subcontractors, and the amount of work actually undertaken on each section of tunnel.
  - Bridges, Highways, and Roads: Calumet Skyway Toll Bridge, Part 1, Specifications and Contract Documents, 1956 March (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Bridges, Highways, and Roads: Calumet Skyway Toll Bridge, Part 2, Detail Specifications, 1956 January (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Bridges, Highways, and Roads: Road Designs and Standards, Virginia Department of Highways, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Alignment Feasibility, Fort Lincoln New Town Transit Shuttle, 1972 October (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Appendix to Engineering and Feasibility and Development Study, Rapid Transit System and Equipment, 1963 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Construction Program, Metro System, Phase I, March, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Contract Breakdown, Latest Design and Construction Schedule, Phase I and II, 1967 July (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Dimension and Weight Study, Final Report, Table of Contents, 1966 October (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Dimension and Weight Study, Final Report, Scope of Investigation, undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Dimension and Weight Study, Final Report, General Arrangement, undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Dimension and Weight Study, Final Report, Weight Schedule, undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Dimension and Weight Study, Final Report, Center of Gravity, undated (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Dimension and Weight Study, Final Report, Clearance Lines, undated (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Dimension and Weight Study, Final Report, Underfloor Equipment, undated (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Dimension and Weight Study, Final Report, Power Collection, 1966 October (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Dimension and Weight Study, Final Report, Doors, undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Dimension and Weight Study, Final Report, Couplers, undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Dimension and Weight Study, Final Report, Side Skirting, undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Dimension and Weight Study, Final Report, Seats, undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Dimension and Weight Study, Final Report, Train Control System, undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Dimension and Weight Study, Final Report, Control System, undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Dimension and Weight Study, Final Report, Environmental Control, undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Dimension and Weight Study, Final Report, Braking System, undated (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Dimension and Weight Study, Final Report, Parking Brake, undated (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Dimension and Weight Study, Final Report, Car Frame, undated (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Dimension and Weight Study, Final Report, Trucks, undated (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Dimension and Weight Study, Final Report, Wheel Size, undated (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Dimension and Weight Study, Final Report, Load Weighing, undated (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Dimension and Weight Study, Final Report, Inspection Periods, undated (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Dimension and Weight Study, Final Report, Credits, undated (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Dimension and Weight Study, Final Report, Miscellaneous, undated (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Environmental Impact Study, L'Enfant-Pentagon River Crossing Route, 1972 June (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Feasibility of Direct Track Fixation on Unballasted Structures, 1968 June (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - List of SFBARTD Standard Guide Specifications, F1, Masonry, 1967 November (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - List of SFBARTD Standard Guide Specifications, F2, Metals, undated (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - List of SFBARTD Standard Guide Specifications, F3, Carpentry, undated (Box 11, Folder 22)
  - List of SFBARTD Standard Guide Specifications, F4, Moisture Control, undated (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - List of SFBARTD Standard Guide Specifications, F5, Doors, Windows, and Glass, undated (Box 11, Folder 24)
  - List of SFBARTD Standard Guide Specifications, F6, Finishes, undated (Box 11, Folder 25)
  - List of SFBARTD Standard Guide Specifications, F7, Specialties, undated (Box 11, Folder 26)
  - List of SFBARTD Standard Guide Specifications, F8, Mechanical, 1968 October (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - List of SFBARTD Standard Guide Specifications, F9, Electrical, undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - List of SFBARTD Standard Guide Specifications, H1, Topsoiling and Finish Grading, undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - List of SFBARTD Standard Guide Specifications, H2, Irrigation Systems, undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - List of SFBARTD Standard Guide Specifications, H3, Planting, undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - NCTA Engineering Feasibility Report, Revised Downtown Rapid Transit System, 1967 February (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - NCTA Engineering Plans and Cost Estimates, Engineering Supplement, Transit Development Program for 1965, 1965 January (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - NCTA Engineering Study, Difficult Ground Tunneling Techniques, 1962 December (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Safety Review of WMATA/B&O Operations in the A-15/A-17 Common Corridor, undated (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Section B-5, Demolition of WTC Yard Facilities, 1Z4213, 1970 October (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Soft Ground Tunneling Driving Methods in the USA, 1962 December (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - South Hills Transit Expressway Revenue Line, 1970 July (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Trackwork Study, Volume II, Recommended Trackwork Standards, 1968 August (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Rail Rapid Transit, Route Designs: Section A-3, Connecticut Avenue, 1A0031, Amendments 1-7, 1970 June (Box 13, Folder 3)